A Guide to the Sidney Lanier Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6957-a
Sidney Lanier Collection 1875-1894
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6957-a
15 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1964 February 24
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem: "Solace", [1867-1881]; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Published as "A Song of Eternity in Time"]
  - Poem: "Solace" (second verse), 1881 April; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Published as "A Song of Eternity in Time." Written to Mrs. Fred M. Steele. ]
  - Poem: "Clover", [1876]; AMsS, 7 p.
    [In memory of John Keats]
  - Poem: "The Stirrup-Cup", [1877]; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem: "A Florida Ghost", [1877]; AMsS, 6 p.
- Letters
  - Sidney Lanier to Mariquita da G. A. de la Figaniere Peacock, 1875 Mar 14; ALS, 3 p. w/typed copy
    [Speaks of his miserable trip from Philadelphia to Baltimore. Explains that an attack of pleurodyraia has kept him from thanking her sooner. Sends greetings to Gibson Peacock. Mentions Edward Jenkins,
    Grinx's Baby: His birth and Other Misfortunes
    , and Dante Alighieri. ]
  - Sidney Lanier to John McDowell Leavitt[?], 1878 Dec 4; ALS, 1 p. w/2 typed copies
    [Mentions his paper, "A Forgotten English Poet," about Bartholomew Griffin, which he sent through A. S. Barnes & Co. and wanted offered to
    International Review
    . Asks if it has arrived, as he has received no acknowledgment.]
  - Sidney Lanier to unknown, 1879 Jun 29; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends two poems, "Sunset" and another, as more representative than anything he sent before. Says they will be better than "Betrayal," which is one of the songs from "The Jacquerie." Notes that "Sunset" was set to music by Dudley Buck after it appeared in
    Lippincott's Magazine
    the second poem was published in
    Scribner's Monthly
    . Thanks correspondent for article on Paul Hamilton Hayne. ]
  - Sidney Lanier to Charles Scribner's Sons, 1880 Mar 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks for the
    Portfolio of Proof Impressions
    . Says that the world is indebted for their work with wood-engraving. He particularly likes the one of Ralph Waldo Emerson. ]
  - Mary Day Lanier to Mr. Hayes, 1883 Sep 24; ALS, 4 p.
    [Sends Sidney Lanier's poem "Strange Jokes," discussing it briefly and asking for word on it soon. Thanks him for letter. Says that few realize that Lanier's genius "was of that order which must make laws unto itself." Claims illness prevented her writing more fully. Mentions [William Hand] Browne, Joseph's brethren, William Kirkus. ]
  - Mary Day Lanier to John Eliot Bowen, 1884 Dec 30; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says she has tried to fulfill Mrs. Strickland's wish, but only this verse remained, as she has stored most of the original poems in Baltimore. She has added Sidney Lanier's signature from a letter. Adds that she is sending them to him as she feels his office can add something from William Hayes Ward. ]
  - Mary Day Lanier to William Elliot Griffis, 1887 Dec 7; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks him for his letter. Expresses a desire to see him. Mentions traveling for her health, and her father Charles Day's death. Tells of her friend Lt. John McIntosh Kell, who served with Commodore Matthew Calbraith Perry on the expedition to Japan. Thanks for his description of his pastoral work. Says she would like to complete the amendments to his copy of
    The English Novel
    . ]
  - Mary Day Lanier to Henry Paret, 1894 Jun 25; ALS, 6 p. w/env
    [Apologizes for not handling his request sooner. Says she has assumed that everything she sent must be accompanied by Sidney Lanier's signature and she can't find anything with his later handwriting. Gives a brief analysis of Lanier's handwriting over the years. Paret may keep enclosed title page to
    How to Read Chaucer
    , and envelopes. Suggests he contact Daniel Coit Gilman. Says that
    was never completed because Lanier waited to find a publisher before he started.]
  - Mary Day Lanier to William Elliot Griffis, n. y. May 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says she is a guest of Sara Thorpe Bull for a few days and would like to meet him. Expresses gratitude for his friendship to Sidney Lanier. ]
- Miscellaneous
  - Envelope addressed to Mary Day Lanier(in Sidney Lanier's handwriting), care of her brother Henry Coit Day, n. y. April 23; Envelope